CHRIS MARTIN

Data Scientist/Analyst

Houston, TX = (214) 770-1127 = chrisjmartin1212@gmail.com = LinkedIn

I'm an adaptable innovator in data science with proven success discovering patterns and deploying holistic project management to convey layers of disparate information. I'm an agile learner able to create order from chaos, absorb new technology quickly, and mine, manipulate, and cleanse data. I deploy professional communications experience and a diverse background to intelligently convey and brainstorm approaches to ordering data. As a strategic forward-thinker adept at conceptualizing options and homing in on efficiencies and best practices, I have experience providing cohesive, consistent documentation to steer initiatives as a constructive, respected team member.

SKILLS

Coding: SQL, JSON, HTML, CSS, XML, Python, R, NumPy, Pandas, Scikit-learn

<u>Data Visualization:</u> Power BI, Matplotlib, Seaborn, Folium, Plot.ly

Software Platforms/Packages: Databricks, Microsoft Azure, Spark, Microsoft Excel, Google Sheets

Statistical Methods: Hypothesis Testing, Probabilities, Confidence Intervals, Bayesian Statistics

Programming: API calls, Command Line Programming, Natural Language Processing, Object-Oriented

Programming, Web Scraping, Big Data Manipulation, Git, Atom

Machine Learning: Neural Networks, Linear/Logistic Regression, Classification, Feature Engineering,

K-Nearest Neighbors, Model Evaluation, Cross-Validation

<u>Additional Skills:</u> Critical Thinking, Cross-Functional Collaboration, Startup Ethos, Team Building, Problem Solving, Research Agility, Presentations

RELEVANT EXPERIENCE

DATA SCIENCE IMMERSIVE Spring, TX - 2021

Acquired, cleaned, and explored large datasets using Python, SQL, and R in order to present findings to both technical and non-technical audiences.

Completed a Capstone project which explored the correlation between quarterly outcomes of NFL games and the eventual winners of those contests.

Constructed a model to better predict structural damage to buildings in earthquake-prone areas in Nepal.

Developed a Natural Language Processing model to classify subreddit posts.

Completed 18 labs focused on real-world applications of data science principles and best practices.

THE DATA INITIATIVE - Scottsdale, AZ - 2018 to 2020

Updated and maintained a database of more than 10,000 documents, web pages, publications, and other files for a startup enterprise enabling deep financial research, analysis, and insights. As the first data employee hired, thoughtfully organized and managed datasets to enable peers and customers seamless access to a labyrinth of international financial information surrounding a particular entity.

- Supported company experts by providing requested data compilations and completing ad hoc data-related projects. Collaborated to transform and manipulate data for accurate, effective display on the web-based platform.
- Administered THE DATA INITIATIVE's Microsoft Azure cloud computing service, including user permissions, data storage, processor operation, resource management, and cost-monitoring.
- Designed and created internal processes to improve efficiency in procuring, curating, and distributing data within the company and onto the platform.
- Combined three disparately organized datasets listing cannabis-licensed businesses in California into a single, standardized master database. Endeavored to connect the commonalities of databases amid ever-changing laws and regulations, using data cleansing, manipulation, and integration techniques. Brought order to the disjointed data of a growing industry.
- Identified, implemented, and trained colleagues on specific web-based tools to increase efficiency and productivity.
- Leveraged existing data to design and create illustrative, informative charts highlighting important trends for clients.
- Revised, documented, and flowcharted complex methodology files, including metrics and formulas, for a
 proprietary algorithm that ranks nations based on their risks for money laundering. Ensured the risk index was
 operating correctly.

INDIVIDUAL PROJECTS

ScoreSquare - Fountain Hills, AZ - 2013 to 2016

Integrated a love of both patterns and sports to create, develop, and promote ScoreSquare, an interactive, sports-themed online prediction game.

- Employed extensive use of self-taught SQL, PHP, and HTML with additional Python and Java to build a website, database, and user-friendly portal.
- Performed quality assurance testing to improve game-playing experience.

INTERESTS

Sports Public Address Announcing (2009-2020): Los Angeles Angels of Anaheim (MLB spring training), SMU men's/women's basketball (NCAA), FC Dallas (MLS)

Live Sports Broadcasting (1991-2020): SMU Football (TV), SMU men's/women's basketball (TV), High School Football and other sports (TV/Radio/Internet), amateur soccer (TV)

EDUCATION

DATA SCIENCE IMMERSIVE Spring, TX = 2021

MICROSOFT DATA SCIENCE PROGRAM Fountain Hills, AZ • 2017-2018

TEXAS CHRISTIAN UNIVERSITY - Fort Worth, TX - 1987-1991